Preliminary Guide to the Charles Schuchert Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Schuchert papers
1859-1943
1884-1943
MS 435
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
26
(52 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, financial papers, diary, a manuscript autobiography, photographs and memorabilia. The major part of the papers is made up of Schuchert's professional correspondence while curator of the geological collections at the Peabody Museum at Yale (1904-1923). Subsequent correspondence is related to his work in the field of paleontology. Also in the papers is the incoming correspondence of Charles Emerson Beecher, Schuchert's predecessor at the Peabody Museum. Schuchert's autobiography (ca. 300 pages) was first written in 1917 and revised in 1940. His photograph albums contain pictures of geological expeditions (ca. 1890-1910) as well as personal and family pictures.
Schuchert, Charles, 1858-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles Schuchert Papers were transferred from the Peabody Museum to the University Library in 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Schuchert Papers consist of twenty-five linear feet of correspondence, financial papers, photographs, memorabilia, a diary and a manuscript autobiography. The papers have not been processed, but three-fourths of the boxes contain professional correspondence organized as follows:
Boxes 2-30: Incoming, pre-1903 to 1942, alphabetical for each year
Boxes 31-39: Outgoing, 1904 to 1942, chronological throughout
Box 1 contains letters addressed to C.E. Beecher, Schuchert's predecessor as curator of geology in the Peabody Museum. Additional Schuchert correspondence is mixed with other papers in boxes 40-51.
The Charles Schuchert Papers were transferred from the Peabody Museum to the University Library in 1967.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Schuchert: Paleontologist; assistant to paleontologists, 1885-1891; participated in a geological survey of Minnesota, 1891-1892; preparer of fossils, Yale University, 1892-1893; assistant paleontologist, U.S. Geological Survey, 1893-1894; M.A. Hon. Yale 1904; LL.D. New York Univ. 1914; SC.D. Yale 1930; S.D. Hon. Harvard 1935. Curator Geology 1904-23; Chairman Dept. Geological Sciences 1919-21; Curator Invertebrate Paleontology 1923-26; Prof. Paleontology and Historical Geology 1904-23; Prof. Emeritus 1923-42; Acting Dean Graduate School 1914-16; Trustee Peabody Museum of Natural History 1912-26; Silliman Lect. 1917-18.
Historical Register of Yale University, 1937-1951.
For more biographical information see Carl P. Dunbar's "Memorial to Charles Schuchert" in Box 1 and Schuchert's manuscript autobiography in Box 42.
Geological surveys; Geology -- United States; Paleontology; Science; Autobiographies; Diaries; Paleontologists; Beecher, Charles Emerson, 1856-1904; Schuchert, Charles, 1858-1942; Peabody Museum of Natural History; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Dunbar, Carl O. "Memorial to Carles Schuchert" (Box 1)
  - Incoming correspondence to C.E. Beecher, Schuchert's predecessor at the Peabody Museum (Box 1)
  - Incoming correspondence [to Schuchert] (Box 1)
    - Unsorted, Pre-1903, 1903-05 (Box 2)
    - A-Z, 1905 (Box 3)
    - A-K, 1906-07 (Box 3)
    - L-Z, 1906-07 (Box 4)
    - A-M, 1908-09 (Box 4)
    - N-Z, 1908-09 (Box 5)
    - A-L, 1910 (Box 5)
    - M-Z, 1910 (Box 6)
    - A-Z, 1911 (Box 6)
    - A-Z, 1912 (Box 7)
    - A-Z, 1913 (Box 8)
    - A-Z, 1914 (Box 9)
    - A-Z, 1915 (Box 10)
    - A-Z, 1916 (Box 11)
    - A-K, 1917 (Box 11)
    - L-Z, 1917 (Box 12)
    - A-Z, 1918 (Box 12)
    - A-Z, 1919 (Box 13)
    - A-Z, 1920 (Box 14)
    - A-Z, 1921 (Box 15)
    - A-Z, 1922 (Box 16)
    - A-F, 1923 (Box 16)
    - G-Z, 1923 (Box 17)
    - A-C, 1924-25 (Box 17)
    - D-Q, 1924-25 (Box 18)
    - R-Z, 1924-25 (Box 19)
    - A-D, 1926-27 (Box 19)
    - E-S, 1926-27 (Box 20)
    - T-Z, 1926-27 (Box 21)
    - A-L, 1928-29 (Box 21)
    - M-Z, 1928-29 (Box 22)
    - A-C, 1930-31 (Box 22)
    - D-Z, 1930-31 (Box 23)
    - A-K, 1932-33 (Box 24)
    - L-Z, 1932-33 (Box 25)
    - A-D, 1934-35
    - E-V, 1934-35 (Box 26)
    - U-Z, 1934-35 (Box 27)
    - A-J, 1936-37 (Box 27)
    - K-Z, 1936-37 (Box 28)
    - A-S, 1938-40 (Box 29)
    - T-Z, 1938-40 (Box 30)
    - A-Z, 1941-42 (Box 30)
  - Outgoing correspondence [from Schuchert] (copybooks)
    - 1904 May 16-1907 Jan 29 (Box 31)
    - 1907 Jan 29-1910 Oct 3 (Box 32)
    - 1910 Oct 3-1913 Jun 4 (Box 33)
    - 1913 Jun 4-1915 Oct 13 (Box 34)
    - 1915 Oct 13-1919 Jan 8 (Box 35)
    - 1919 Jan 10-1921 May 30 (Box 36)
    - 1921 Jun 3-1925 Jul 9 (Box 37)
    - 1925 Jul 9-1932 Dec 6 (Box 38)
    - 1932 Dec 12-1942 Oct 9 (Box 39)
  - Cancelled checks, royalty statements, Museum reports, address file, 1920s-1940s (Box 40)
  - Medals, checkbooks, correspondence, financial papers, photograph of Schuchert as a child, 1859, 1890s-1940s (Box 41)
  - Family correspondence, photographs, autobiographical materials, manuscript of autobiography, 1920s, 1930s (Box 42)
    General note
    See also: Chapters in the manuscript "Autobiography of Charles Schuchert" Box 42
  - Correspondence, autobiographical materials, Hayden award, 1890s, 1900s, 1929 (Box 43)
  - Correspondence, 1890s (Box 44)
  - Diary, award materials, material re: retirement from Peabody Museum, 1904, 1926, 1930s (Box 45)
  - Degrees, clippings, family coat of arms, 1920s, 1930s (Box 46)
  - Photograph and postard albums re: geology, travel, 1900s-1910s (Box 47, Box 47A)
  - Photograph and postcards, clippings, undated (Box 48)
  - Photograph albums re: geological expeditions, 1890s-1910s (Box 49)
  - Photographs of geologists, 1894, undated (Box 49A, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs of geologists, clipping file, undated (Box 50)
  - Phographs of Schuchert and family, undated (Box 51)
  - Degrees, honors, photographs of Schuchert, 1914, 1920s, 1939 (Box 52)
  - Chapters in the manuscript "Autobiography of Charles Schuchert"
    Scope and Contents
    "First written Fall of 1917. Amended February 1935. Completely revised in August 1940."
    The manuscript of Charles Schuchert's autobiography is in Box 42.
    - Chapter I. My German Ancestors (Box 42)
    - Chapter II. My Mother and Her Ancestry
      - Sub-section -My Sisters and Brothers (Box 42)
    - Chapter III. The Pioneers of the Ohio Valley and La Belle Riviere (Box 42)
    - Chapter IV. Rise to Manhood at Cincinnati (Box 42)
    - Chapter V. Education (Box 42)
    - Chapter VI. Business Career (Box 42)
    - Chapter VII. First Steps in Paleontology (Box 42)
    - Chapter VIII. My Service wth Professor James Hall (& another copy marked duplicate, but only 27p.) (Box 42)
    - Appendix I & II (Box 42)
    - Group of added unorganized notes (Box 42)